<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ecgu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ecgu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-06T02:20:40+00:00</updated><id>https://ecgu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Eric Gu</title><subtitle>PhD student at UC Irvine </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Using RSS Feeds for Anthropology Journals (And Where to Find Them)</title><link href="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2026/rss-for-journals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using RSS Feeds for Anthropology Journals (And Where to Find Them)"/><published>2026-01-05T16:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-05T16:32:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2026/rss-for-journals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2026/rss-for-journals/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="what-is-rss-and-why-use-it">What is RSS and why use it?</h4> <p>If you’re like me and don’t like notifications for new journal publications flooding your email, I recommend looking into an RSS feed. RSS, or Really Simple Syndication, is a way to keep up with updates on websites of your choice through one standardized format. It’s quick to learn, easy to set up, and plus, it’s free! RSS feeds have been around for a long time, and it’s what most apps use to update episodes for podcasts.</p> <p>Unfortunately, the problem is that RSS feeds are not great for monetization, since it means you can access a website’s content without directly interacting with it; Facebook removed RSS feeds in 2011, Google shut down their RSS service, Google Reader, in 2013, and Elon Musk removed it after he bought Twitter. For the websites of acaemic journals, they can make RSS feeds very difficult to find if they haven’t removed them outright. This is strange to me, especially when so many websites for journals have the option to share articles on Facebook for some reason, and also have bots on Twitter that post article updates into the void with 0 likes. I wonder if sites intentionally want people to not use RSS feeds so make you register an account for every site or sign-up for e-mail subscriptions instead to keep better track of user information (for good reasons, of course).</p> <p>However, as our internet experiences are increasingly bogged down by advertisements, sensationalist news, AI slop, and whatever else recommendation algorithms decide to push your way, RSS is becoming a <a href="https://archive.is/20200208081939/https://www.wired.com/story/rss-readers-feedly-inoreader-old-reader/#selection-659.56-912.0">refreshingly boring alternative</a>. On one page, I can see all the journals I am interested in, without dealing with the particularities of each website or without fear of forgetting to save a journal in my bookmarks:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/feedbrosample-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/feedbrosample-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/feedbrosample-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/feedbrosample.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The list of journals I follow are on the left, list of new articles in the center, and a preview of the article is on the right. Pretty neat! </div> <p>Of course, I can also use RSS feeds to keep up with the news, follow blogs and new book releases from publishers and more:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/otherfeed-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/otherfeed-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/otherfeed-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/otherfeed.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Here I can keep up with the job board for Anthropology Careers &amp; Employment! </div> <p>I’m not alone in advocating for a return to RSS in anthropology either: see <a href="https://www.gjotsuki.net/reconstructing-the-anthro-blogosphere-with-rss/">Grant Otsuki’s guide to RSS feeds for anthropology blogs</a>, which makes a much more eloquent case for blogs and RSS as a way to build online community for anthropology and academia without relying on sites like Twitter.</p> <h4 id="how-to-set-up-an-rss-reader">How to set up an RSS reader</h4> <p>RSS is not an app, but a way of formatting data that can be displayed in different ways. This means you get to choose how to use RSS feeds in the “feed aggregator” or “content reader” of your choice, on whatever device or browser of your choice. My personal preference is <a href="FeedBro Reader for Firefox">https://nodetics.com/feedbro/</a>, which is free and can be easily accessed through Firefox on my laptop (you can use it on Chrome too). It also comes with a plug-in that searches for RSS feeds on any site you’re on, although it doesn’t work too well for academic journal indexing sites. Other options include <a href="https://netnewswire.com/">NetNewsWire</a> (iOS; free and <a href="https://itsfoss.com/what-is-foss/">open-source</a>), <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> (web, Android, and iOS; requires an account and has some AI stuff), and <a href="https://www.inoreader.com/">Inoreader</a> (Android and IOS; requires an account and has a free tier). Once you have one downloaded, you’re ready to add feeds to it!</p> <h4 id="how-to-add-feeds-to-an-rss-reader">How to add feeds to an RSS reader</h4> <p>If you’ve ever seen this orange icon on a website before, that’s the RSS icon! Click on it to get the link to the RSS feed. Just copy-paste the link into your reader of choice and you’ll be good to go.</p> <p>Some sites like Project Muse have a <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/feeds/list_feeds?type=article">neat list of RSS feeds for all the journals that they host</a>:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/musefeednarrow-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/musefeednarrow-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/musefeednarrow-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/musefeednarrow.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Careful, collecting feeds can be like collecting books for the shelf... </div> <p>For others, they might be on the side of the main page for the journal:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/critrss-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/critrss-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/critrss-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/critrss.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Some of them, while keeping RSS feeds in name, go through obtuse lengths to hide links to them. This includes in the University of Chicago:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/chicagorss-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/chicagorss-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/chicagorss-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/chicagorss.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> I wonder why the icon is in the About section... </div> <p>And Berghahn:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/bergahnwhere-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/bergahnwhere-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/bergahnwhere-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/bergahnwhere.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Now where could it be? </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/bergahnreveal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/bergahnreveal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/bergahnreveal-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/bergahnreveal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> There it is, at the bottom of the sidebar! </div> <p>There are some journals and hosting websites that disappointingly don’t seem to provide any RSS feed at all, so you’ll have to just follow them the old fashioned way. The wall of shames includes:</p> <ul> <li>All of Duke University Press (<em>Public Culture</em>, <em>Social Text</em>, <em>Boundary 2</em>, etc)</li> <li>All of University of California Press (although <em>Representations</em> has its own)</li> <li><em>The Journal of American Ethnology</em>; Strangely, <em>Cultural Anthropology</em> which is also hosted by AnthroSource has an RSS feed in plain sight, but American Ethnology doesn’t!</li> </ul> <p>If this changes or you find their RSS feeds somewhere, feel free to email me!</p> <p>You can also find compilations of RSS feeds others have already made in an OPML file format. Simply download the file and import it into your reader. My list of RSS feeds for academic journals, which revolve around anthropology, media studies, and Asian area studies is here. You can also add or delete feeds to your liking; if you make a list of your own for other disciplines or subfields, don’t hesitate to share it with others! If you run into technical issues, I’m always open to meet new people, so don’t be afraid to drop a message to me either! Good luck!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academia"/><category term="academia"/><category term="anthropology"/><category term="howto"/><category term="rss"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What RSS feeds are, how to set them up to follow your favorite academic journals, and a rant about accessibility]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ecgu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>